<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The atheist unmasked, or, A confutation of such as deny the being of a supream deity that governs heaven and earth by unanswerable arguments deduc'd ... / by ---- a person of honour.</title>
            <author>Person of honour.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1685</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 56 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 12 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A26122</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing A4108</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R16362</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12255940</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12255940</idno>
            <idno type="VID">57480</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A26122)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 57480)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 163:14)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The atheist unmasked, or, A confutation of such as deny the being of a supream deity that governs heaven and earth by unanswerable arguments deduc'd ... / by ---- a person of honour.</title>
                  <author>Person of honour.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 21 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Langley Curtiss ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1685.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Errata: t.p., verso.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
                  <note>(from t.p.) 1. From the receiv'd principles of natural reason --2. The consent of all nations who own and worship a God (though some mistake the right object) -- 3. From the certainty of Scripture history (the most authentick record in the world) -- 4. From divers reasons drawn from other topic's, all design'd to prevent the growth of atheism, the worst of heresies.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Atheism --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:57480:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:57480:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE ATHEIST Unmasked, OR A Confutation of ſuch as deny the Being of a SUPREAM DEITY, that governs HEAVEN and EARTH. BY <hi>Unanſwerable Arguments deduc'd.</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>1. <hi>From the receiv'd Principles of Natural Reaſon.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. <hi>The Conſent of all Nations, who own and Worſhip a God (though ſome miſtake the Right object.)</hi>
               </item>
               <item>3. <hi>From the certainty of Scripture Hiſtory, (the moſt Authentick Record in the World) And,</hi>
               </item>
               <item>4. <hi>From divers Reaſons drawn from other Topic's — All deſign'd to prevent the growth of Atheiſm the worſt of Hereſies.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>By — A Perſon of Honour.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Pſalm. 14.1.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>The Fool hath ſaid in his heart, there is no God. <hi>ſee Pſal. 10.4. &amp; 53.1.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>Langley Curtiſs</hi> at Sir <hi>Edmondbury-Godfreys Head</hi> near <hi>Fleet-bridge.</hi> 1685.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:57480:2"/>
            <head>An ERRATA.</head>
            <p>SEveral groſs Faults are COmitted by the neglect of the Preſs, which the Reader is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired to Correct with his Pen, as in P. 3. l. 4. for <hi>will,</hi> read <hi>would,</hi> P. 4. l. 6. for uncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptible, read contemptible Fiſhermen, P. 6. l. 1. for hearts read hearers, l. 13. for Jnju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, read Enemies, P. 10. l. 3. for ſatisfactions, read ſatisfactory, <hi>idem.</hi> P. l. 11. for Dumb, read Dim'd, <hi>idem</hi> P. l. 18. for ſeveral, read even all, <hi>idem</hi> P. l. 23. and 24. for <hi>Andragoras,</hi> read <hi>Anaxagoras,</hi> and for <hi>Eumerus,</hi> read <hi>Euemerus,</hi> P. 12. l. 18. for, and then Incite, read and Cite, P. 13. l. 24. for elimate, read eliminate, P. 14. for <hi>Eumerus,</hi> read <hi>Euemerus, idem</hi> P. l. 17. for <hi>Antioche,</hi> read <hi>Antiochenus,</hi> P. 18. l. the Laſt, for bewitched, read bewildred, P. 19. l. 25. for, and has no end, read has no end, P. 21. l. 7. for an intelligible Riddle, read an untelligible Riddle, <hi>idem</hi> P. l. 11. for extradate, read extraduce.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:57480:2"/>
            <head>THE ATHEIST UNMASKED, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THat there ſhould be any ſuch Monſter in nature, as for a Man, who pretends to be a reaſonable Creature, to deny there is a God, is an Impiety out-does the Devils, who believe and trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble; but Hiſtorians and Writings of former times have told us, there were ſuch amongſt the Heathens, and good Authors and ſad experience do aſſure us, that ſuch have been and are in the times of Chriſtianity, Saint <hi>Jude</hi> tells us, that in the laſt times, there ſhall be Mockers liv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing after their own Luſts, ungodly Men that turn the grace of God into wantoneſs, denying God our only Lord, and our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, and I find a Learned and Pious Biſhop of <hi>Saliſbury,</hi> who has written an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent treatiſe againſt it, ſadly bewailing the growth of it, above three<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcore Years ſince; and ſayes, though it be a thing ſo neceſſary to be believed that there is a God, yet leaſt laboured in by Divines to farther our belief, and though our Church be ſtored with ſome excellent Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter Builders and Learned Men, yet few or none ſets his hand to this, many work upon the walls to make them firm and ſtrong, many upon the roof to keep it cloſe and light, ſome beautifie and adorn it, but none looks down into the ground work of it, that it be laid ſo low, as to reach unto the Rock, whereby there is a ſpace left for Pioneers and Underminers, and ſuch like deceitful Workers, which are not able to
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:57480:3"/>break through the Walls, yet do dig under the Foundation to evert all, and complains that this argument is the moſt deſerted part of all Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logy, and wherein feweſt Divines have beſtowed their pains, the more is the pitty, which puts me in mind of the Parable in the Goſpel, of the Man that ſowed good ſeed in his Field, and whilſt he ſlept, the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my came and ſowed Tares, ſo be the ſeed never ſo good and well ſown, yet if it be neglected and we ſleep, the Enemy win take advantage to ſow his Tares, and if little or no notice be taken of him, he will grow bold and think himſelf in the right: But I muſt not ſtay upon generalls, reſolving to confine my diſcourſe into a very narrow compaſs, for I ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve the fate of long tracts to be fruitleſs in a great meaſure, becauſe the price deterrs moſt from buying, and the length from reading, I muſt be forced alſo, if I have hope of prevailing with or againſt the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theiſt, to looſe the advantage of Scripture proofs in a great meaſure, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he denies the Scriptures to be of God, but to be only humane inventions to cozen the People, ſo that it would be to caſt Pearls before Swine, to trample them under their feet.</p>
            <p>But by the Atheiſts leave, 'tis very unreaſonable for him not to give the Scripture ſo antient an Hiſtory, that Hiſtorical Faith, that he does to <hi>Plutarch, Livie</hi> and other Hiſtoriographers, who takes for truth what they write, becauſe he cannot accuſe the Authors of falſhood, and for him to ſay the Scriptures are the contrivances of Men, unleſs he could by ſome demonſtration or probable argument make it appear ſo, is a pittiful ſhift, if they had been ſuch, the prying Atheiſt, and his ſpawn the Deboſhee would long ſince have detected it, and we ſhould have heard of it with both Eares, all that he can poſſibly object muſt be, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they that wrote them were deceivers, or were themſelves deceiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; I'le firſt inſtance the <hi>New Teſtament,</hi> which the Atheiſt moſt ſlights, and therein the Four Evangeliſts, who write the Life and Death, and Reſurrection of Chriſt, whoſoever weighes their Writings, and conſiders what good Precepts there are of Love, Charity, Meekneſs, Patience, Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility, Obedience to Magiſtrates and Parents, and what threatnings to Wickedneſs; Debauchery, Whoredom, Swearing, Lying, Drunkenneſs, and all evil; muſt certainly conclude they were not deceivers, the <hi>Jews</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed as mortal Enemies to Chriſt and his Diſciples, as the Atheiſt en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavoured to make the World believe they and their Maſter were ſuch, but the Reſurrection of Chriſt galled them, for when they found he was riſen from the Grave, and his Tomb empty, they raged extreamly,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:57480:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>and were cut to the heart; well knowing, that if his Reſurrection ſhould be admitted, that would juſtifie Chriſt and his Apoſtles, and condemn themſelves for Malefactors in Crucifying him, as the Council told the Apoſtles <hi>Act.</hi> 5. <hi>You will bring this Mans Blood upon us.</hi> then if the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection of Chriſt, which is the Foundation of all Religion can by any probable demonſtration be cleared, the Atheiſt muſt acknowledge there is a God, and his Apoſtles not deceivers; therefore I'le only inſiſt upon that, which to prevent the World from believing, they thought the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bableſt way was to corrupt the Watch that kept the Sepulchre (with aſſurance of indemnity) to ſay his Diſciples came by Night, and ſtole him away while they ſlept, this is a very improbable tale, and carries fiction in the fore-head, for 'tis clear Chriſt was Buried on the <hi>Fryday,</hi> and there was no Watch ſet till the Night following, then ſurely, if his Diſciples would have ſtollen him away, they would have done it the firſt Night when there was no Watch ſet <hi>Mat.</hi> 27.62. and indeed 'tis too incredible they could do it, and too too incredible they would do it.</p>
            <p>'Tis too too incredible they could do it, after ſo vigilent, diligent, and abundant Watch was ſet, which doubtleſs was of the keeneſt ſort againſt Chriſt, and that was enough to keep them awake, it being but one Night they watched, and if they had been aſleep, the rolling away the Stone from the Sepulchre, which was a great one, taking of the things he was wrapped in, and carrying him away muſt needs have wakened ſome of them, and ſurely if they had ſtollen him, they would have ſtollen the Linnen alſo with him for the more haſt, St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> gives a clear refutation of that fiction of the Watch, for ſays he, either they ſlept not and ſo 'tis a lye, or if they did, how could they tell who ſtole him away if it had been ſo; beſides, had they not had aſſurance of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnity, they durſt not have told ſuch a ſtory againſt their lives, for we find upon St. <hi>Peters</hi> miraculous deliverance out of Priſon, the Keepers were Examined and put to death, though Innocent.</p>
            <p>Secondly, 'tis more then too incredible they would do it, would they that being <hi>Jews,</hi> and knew what God and Religion meant, have dared to have Fathered ſuch a groſs Forgery on God, as the Preaching of Obedience up and down the World to a Crucifyed Man, nor otherwiſe riſen from the Dead, than by ſtealing his Body out of his Grave, what hope could they ever have of any ſucceſs, no hope from him whom they Preached, whoſe own conſciences muſt tell them, he was yet in
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:57480:4"/>the Power of Death, no hope from God whom they ſo falſly belyed, no hope from any thing in themſelves, not from eloquence and excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency of ſpeech to perſwade, they were but rude and illiterate men, not from Wealth and Riches to corrupt, ſhooes on their feet, and a ſtaffe in their hand was moſt of what they had, not from authority and greatneſs to awe or prejudice, they were but uncontemptible Fiſhermen and the like, not from number or multitude to ſubdue, they were but Eleven poor Snakes, that had all run away when their Maſter was apprehended, nor hope therefore from any thing in themſelves.</p>
            <p>No hope farther from any docibleneſs or inclinableneſs of the Parties to be perſwaded, not any inclinableneſs in the <hi>Jews,</hi> not him but <hi>Barabbas,</hi> and Crucifie him, Crucifie him, was the loud and joint cry of the <hi>Jews,</hi> the <hi>Jews</hi> was hardened therefore againſt any ſuch Doctrine, not any in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clinableneſs in the Gentiles, it was that they mocked at when they heard of the Reſurrection, would they therefore, that were no ſtark fools have gone about a thing of ſo great folly, wherein they had no hope of ſucceſs from him, they Preached as not Riſen, no hope from God as belyed by them, no hope from any thing in themſelves, as being without Eloquence, without Riches, without Authority, without Multitude, nor hope from any inclinableneſs in the Parties, to be perſwaded <hi>Jews</hi> or <hi>Gentiles,</hi> as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing utter Enemies, the one to the mention of <hi>Jeſus</hi> of <hi>Nazareth,</hi> the other to the mention of the Reſurrection.</p>
            <p>But ſuppoſe they had been ſo overſeen, as not to have conſidered theſe things at the firſt, would they not when the ſtorm began to fall on them, and the World to riſe up in Arms againſt them, ſeeing the impoſſibility of making their legend, their lying legend take, would they not then have deſiſted, would not fair nor foul means have made of them at the leaſt, at laſt to have bewrayed the whole buſineſs, but all their life long in ſpite of what the World could do, they ſhould continue every one of them in the conſtant aſſeveration of the Reſurrection of Chriſt, certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly had they been nothing but deceivers, it is not imaginable, that the World could have a pack of ſuch, except they had been Incarnate De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils, but their Writings and much more their Lives, ſhew them rather to have been Incarnate Angels.</p>
            <p>Nor were they deceived, for firſt they were ſure the Body was not in the Sepulchre, their own ſenſe, and the ſenſe of all the <hi>Jews</hi> viewing the empty Sepulchre confirm'd them of that; ſecondly, they were ſure none had privily ſtollen the Body away, and laid it elſewhere, becauſe of the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:57480:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>Watch that kept the Sepulchre, beſides they were ſure they ſeveral times converſed with him after his Reſurrection, and many eye Witneſſes there were of it beſides themſelves, this I uſe not as a Scripture proof, but on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly upon the reaſons alledged, evidently manifeſting that what they wrote muſt needs be truth, and then moſt certainly they were not deceivers nor deceived, but the Atheiſt farther Cavills, at the difference there ſeems to be amongſt them, in the relation of ſome of the things they write, which is a ſtrong argument to me of their ſincerity, for had they been a pack of Knaves intending to cozen the World, they would ſurely have ſo contrived the matter, that not the leaſt ſeeming difference ſhould have been, and they are indeed but ſeeming, and have been reconciled by the Pens of others, and may be ſo by any unprejudiced underſtanding Read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, <hi>Camer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> de notis verbi Dei,</hi> obſerves that the Scriptures are ſo penn'd, that they that have a mind to know may know, and they that have a mind to wrangle may take occaſion of offence, and juſtly periſh by the Rebellion of their own reaſon, for ſaith he, God never meant to ſatisfie Men, <hi>perfracti ingenii</hi> of a ſtubborn and perverſe wit; <hi>Tertullian</hi> had ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved the ſame long before him, that God had ſo diſpoſed the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, that they that will not be ſatisfyed might be hardened.</p>
            <p>If it had not been the greateſt truth they preached, how came it to paſs, that ſo few contemptible Perſons in the World, eye ignorant Men, and wholly illiterate ſhould within the ſpace of about Twenty Years af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Chriſts Sufferings, have converted almoſt all the known parts of the World to their Doctrine, a World ſo captived under Satan, a World ſo corrupted in manners, and ſo rooted and habituated in ſuperſtitious cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomes, was it not ſtrange, that without any other Sword than the ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Goſpel, they ſhould turn the World upſide down, as their Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies themſelves confeſſed, ſlighting the Devils works, caſting down his holds wherever they came, and overcoming thoſe barbarous Heathens, whom the Devil had held in his peaceable poſſeſſion ſo many Thouſand Years, to renounce their Idolatries, in which they had been bred and train'd up all their days, to receive a new Lord, and him a Crucified Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, and this at the report of a few ſilly Men, laden with the vileſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaches that the wit of Man can invent, or malice rak'd together to beſmear their Perſons, and render the Doctrine they Preached odious to the World: This is ſuch a kind of Conqueſt, as could not be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained by any leſs than the Arm of the Almighty; eſpecially if we conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the nature of their Doctrine, that it was not only new, but ſtrange,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:57480:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>enough to make the hearts ſhie of it, as being quite contrary to Mans corrupt Nature; not having one thought in the Sinners heart to befriend it, a Doctrine pure non-ſence to carnal reaſon, teaching to be ſaved by anothers Righteouſneſs, wiſe with anothers wiſedom, to truſt in him as a God that was himſelf a Child, to relye on him to deliver us from the Power of Sin and Satan, that fell himſelf under the wrath of Men, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider how little Worldly encouragement it gave to his Diſciples, 1. not to grow rich, but rather to let what they had, 2. not to gain the Love of the World, but to be hated, 3. not to enjoy the pleaſures of the World, but the Croſs, a Goal, a Dungeon, a Gibbet or Rack, yet to ſee poor Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures ſo far, to forget all their Worldly intereſts, relations, eſtates, and enjoyments, ſo as to trample upon them, yea joyfully wellcome the bloodieſt deaths their injuries could invent, and thank their Perſecutors for the favour of admitting them, to ſhare with the torments of their bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, as if they had gone to divide a ſpoil and not to be made one, this ſpeaks a Heavenly Power to be in that Doctrine, which verifies what Chriſt told his Diſciples, John 14. <hi>He that believes on me, the works that I do ſhall he do alſo, and greater works than theſe,</hi> what greater works are theſe, Chriſt cured all diſeaſes, caſt out Devils and raiſed the dead, what great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er works did the Apoſtles, yes, the converſion of the World, and the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion every where of his Kingdom, that is called the Prince of the World were greater works, a far greater work to raiſe up the dead World, then one dead <hi>Lazarus,</hi> to deny then a Goſpel, that has been propagated with a glorious ſucceſs, confirm'd by a frame of Miracles, acknowledged by the Writings of the Heathens, that lived in the Primitive times, wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſed by the Blood of Martyrs, and thoſe of the wiſer and learned ſort, who could not all be a parcel of Melancholy Fools, and ſhall this have not better reception, than if it were a mere Romance and impertinent Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, but if thoſe things, which you will not believe prove true at laſt, that the Son of God has ſuffered by Gods appointment for the capiation of ſin, that thoſe that believe in him, ſhall receive the benefit of it and none elſe, what a madneſs then will you think your ſelves Guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of.</p>
            <p>There is nothing in the Chriſtian Religion, can make againſt your re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al happineſs, (ſuppoſing it were not true) but if it be true, the ſlight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of it expoſes to an unexpreſſible miſery, if the things revelled prove true, when it is too late to gather the bleſſed fruit of them, will a
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:57480:5"/>bottomleſs Lake, or a perpetual ſtinging conſcience be ballanced, by a few tranſitory pleaſures on Earth, is it not unreaſonable folly, to deny a Doctrine you cannot demonſtrate to be falſe, and be in danger to feel a miſery that you cannot demonſtrate, but it may come upon you, rather than to comply with a Doctrine which cannot do you any pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice, in the great concerns of your Souls, ſuppoſing they were not true, 'tis a folly utterly to deny them, till you can demonſtrate there is no ſuch thing as a Redeemer, that the Scripture is not the Word of God, that no ſuch condition as Faith is required of Men.</p>
            <p>The Atheiſt quarrels with the Old Teſtament too, though he muſt confeſs it to be the Antienteſt Hiſtory in the World, and we uſe to give great reverence and credit to Antiquity, if there be no juſt ground to blemiſh it, which the Atheiſt cannot produce to weigh with the mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt underſtanding, that the Old Teſtament is the Word of God, though it have been abundantly evidenced by other hands to be ſo, I ſhall give but one inſtance amongſt many, that the children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> were carryed captive to <hi>Babylon,</hi> and delivered again, other Authors men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion as well as the Bible, <hi>Iſaiah</hi> the Prophet foretells their deliverance, and names the Perſon by whom it ſhould be effected namely <hi>Cyrus,</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove an Hundred Years before <hi>Cyrus</hi> was Born, which came to paſs ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly, ſo the Old Prophet denounced the deſtruction of <hi>Jeroboams</hi> Altar by <hi>Joſiah,</hi> many Years before <hi>Joſiah</hi> was Born, 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 13. c. 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 23.16. this certainly muſt be the Word of God by the Prophets, for Man of himſelf cannot tell what ſhall come to paſs hereafter, nay the Devil himſelf cannot, and we ſee in the 41. of <hi>Iſaiah,</hi> God makes it a particular priviledge of his own; ſaying, <hi>ſhew us the things that are to come hereafter, that we may know you are Gods,</hi> I'le not trouble the Reader with farther inſtances, ſurely none could be the Author of the Bible but God, if any Creature made it, he was either a wicked Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, or one that was Holy, firſt no wicked Creature could do it, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Angel nor Man, ſurely they would never have taken ſo much pains to pull down their own Kingdom of Darkneſs (the great Plot that runs through the Bible, from one end of it to the other.) The impla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cable wrath that the Devil and his party of wicked ones in the World, have ſhewn in all Ages to the Scriptures, declares ſufficiently it never came from them, neither can any Holy Creature be the Author of it be it Angel or Man, can we think that any having the leaſt ſpark of
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:57480:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>Love to God, or fear of his Majeſty, dwelling in their Breaſt, durſt counterfeit his dreadful name, by ſetting it to their work, and abuſe the World with ſuch a Blaſphemy and prodigious Lye, as to ſay, thus ſaith the Lord, and prefix his Name all along, when not God but them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves are the Authors; nay farther, durſt any Holy Creature put ſuch a cheat upon the World, and then denounce the wrath and vengeance of God againſt thoſe, that ſhall ſpeak in Gods Name, but were never ſent of him, as the Scriptures mention, certainly the Earth which ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed up <hi>Corah</hi> and his wicked rout, for pretending to an Authority from God, as good as the Prieſts to offer Incenſe, would not have ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red <hi>Moſes</hi> himſelf, if he had ſpoken that in Gods Name, which he had not from him, but was the invention of his own private Brain.</p>
            <p>But the Atheiſt will have his frivolous pretences, one of his Caviſts is againſt the long lives of Men before the Flood, ſome Seven, Eight, and Nine Hundred Years, and that in few Ages after the Flood, they came to little more than One Hundred, and his inference is, that then there muſt either be a decay in the nature of Man, and a Man of Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven Years of age now muſt have been an Old Man, or elſe the ſtory of their former long lives muſt be falſe, but admitting the long lives of Men before the Flood, which is a certain and undiſprovable truth, I ſhall make it appear, that the reaſon of the diſproportion of Mens lives be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore and after the Flood, did not proceed from any decay in the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of Man, but muſt be attributed to the difference of their Food af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the Flood, from what it was before.</p>
            <p>It muſt be admitted that God made the World, which I ſhall mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt afterward, and that by his Providence he governs it, then 'tis ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional to conclude, that he appointed to every Creature their ſeveral Food, to Man as well as Beaſt, we find <hi>Gen.</hi> 1.29. <hi>That God appointed to Man for his Food every herb bearing ſeed, and every fruit of a tree bear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſeed,</hi> that was to be his meat, but after the Flood Mans Food was enlarged, for <hi>Gen.</hi> 9.3. <hi>God ſaid to</hi> Noah, <hi>every living thing that moveth ſhall be meat to you, even as the green herb have I given you all things,</hi> by which 'tis clear, that Fleſh was not allowed to Man before, and 'tis a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greed by all, that one Months eating of Fleſh, nouriſhes more than ſix with fruits and herbs, and then it muſt neceſſarily follow, that the ſooner nature is heightned, and brought to perfection the ſooner it muſt
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:57480:6"/>decay, and as with their diet before the Flood, Men lived uſually to ſuch an Age, ſo after the Flood, Men have lived much after the ſame rate of Age as they do now, there being to be found now a days, Men uſually living as long as ſeveral Thouſand Years ſince, as ſeveral in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances might be given, even in our own Age, and though the Luxury and intemperance of later Ages, have and does dayly ſhorten ſeveral Mens lives, yet that concerns not the generality of Mankind; <hi>Fuller</hi> writing the life of <hi>Paracelſus</hi> tells us, he dyed at Forty Seaven Years Old, and makes it a wonder, ſo great a Phyſician ſhould dye ſo ſoon, but he makes it as great a wonder ſo drunken a Beaſt ſhould live ſo long, many ſuch inſtances of that and other vices might be given.</p>
            <p>My next Reaſon to prove there is a God is, that 'tis the general conſent of all Nations in all Places and Ages, and then 'tis a madneſs for a few Men to deny what all the World believes, no inſtance can be given of any one People in the World that diſclaim it, whatever diſputes there have been in the World, this of the exiſtence of a God, was never the ſubject of contention, all other things have been queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned, we find the Philoſophers varying about natural things, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided into ſeveral ſects of oppoſition, but there was never any Sect of Atheiſts, and this univerſal conſent is not prejudiced by ſome few Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenters, Hiſtory does not reckon Twenty profeſt Atheiſts in all Ages, in the compaſs of the whole World, and we have not the name of any one abſolute Atheiſt in the Scripture, ſo that the paucity of them, is enough to juſtifie the conſent of all Nations, which by a natural in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct is implanted in them, elſe how ſhould it come to paſs, that all Nations in the World ſo far diſtant from one another, and between whom there was no commerce, ſome not known nor found out till la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Ages, ſo univerſally to agree in it; <hi>Cicero</hi> tells us, that a general conſent of all Nations, is to be eſteemed a Law of nature, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they that aſcribe all to nature, and ſet it in the place of God, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradict themſelves if they give not credit to it, in that which it univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſally affirms.</p>
            <p>Beſides, it has been a conſtant and interrupted conſent, it has been as antient as the firſt Age of the World, no Man is able to mention any time from the beginning of the World, wherein this notion has not been univerſally owned, in the overturning of the Governments of States,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:57480:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>the alteration of the modes of worſhip this has ſtood unſhaken, the reaſons upon which it was founded were in all revolutions of time ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted ſatisfactions and convincings, nor could abſolute Atheiſm in the changes of any Laws, ever gain the favour of any one body of People to be eſtabliſhed by a Law.</p>
            <p>The diſcovery of all other impoſtures, never made this by any ſocie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Men to be ſuſpected as one, it will not be eaſie to name any im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſture, that has walked perpetually in the World without publick con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trol and queſtion, and ſince the World has detected many errors of the former Age, and Learning been increaſed, it has been ſo far from being dumb, that it has ſhone out clearer with the increaſe of natural know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, and received freſh and more vigorous confirmation.</p>
            <p>But ſays the Atheiſt, though ſuch a general conſent ſhould be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, it cannot be affirm'd that all Perſons have therein con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented, becauſe both Heathen and Chriſtian Authors, have mentioned divers that have denyed it, who are not denyed to have been Learned Men, and ranked amongſt the Philoſophers, 'tis a pittiful argument that ſeveral the wiſeſt and learnedeſt Men, and Philoſophers in the World are in an error, becauſe ſo very few and not ſo learned do oppoſe them, for if they be compared with thoſe Learned Men, that either lived be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore them or after them, their Learning will come as far ſhort in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion as the light of a Candle to the brightneſs of the Sun, for what compariſon can <hi>Diagoras</hi> hold with <hi>Pythagoras,</hi> or <hi>Protagoras</hi> with <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dragoras,</hi> or <hi>Eumerus</hi> with <hi>Empedocles,</hi> or <hi>Theodorus</hi> with <hi>Theophraſtus,</hi> or <hi>Bion</hi> with <hi>Chilon,</hi> or <hi>Epicurus</hi> with <hi>Epicarmus</hi> to be ſilent of <hi>Socrates, Plato, Ariſtotle,</hi> and <hi>Zeno,</hi> and abundance of others, which can find no Paralells amongſt the Atheiſts being ſo eminent above them.</p>
            <p>Beſides the fears and anxieties in Mens conſciences, have given Men ſufficient occaſion to root it out had it been poſſible for them to do it, if the notion of the exiſtence of a God had been poſſible to have been daſhed out of the minds of Men, they would have done it rather than have ſuffered ſo many diſquietings in their Souls, upon Commiſſion of their wicked impieties, of which there are many inſtances in all A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges.</p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:57480:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>It muſt be confeſſed by all, that there is a Law of Nature written on the hearts of Men, which will direct them to commendable actions, if they will attend to the writing in their own conſciences, this Law cannot be conſidered without a notice of a Law-giver, for 'tis but a natural and obvious concluſion, that ſome ſuperiour hand ingrafted thoſe Principles in Man, ſince he finds ſomething in him twitching him upon the purſuit of uncomely actions, though his heart be mightily inclined to them, Man knows he never planted this Principle of relu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctancy in his own Soul, and cannot be the cauſe of that he cannot be friends with, if he were the cauſe of it, why does he not rid himſelf of it.</p>
            <p>But the Atheiſt would ſhift of all this by ſaying, that the notice of a God and Religion, came only from Tradition, and the conſpiracy of Governours to keep People in better awe, how fooliſh and futile this conceit is, abundantly appears by the impoſſibility of it, for how could Governours of Nations ſo far diſtant, and not known to each o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and of ſo different intereſt poſſibly agree in ſuch a deſign, or how could they agree in ſuch an univerſal Tradition, that were ſuch ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers to each other, ſurely there muſt be ſometime alledged from whom they had it, and when firſt began, but this fond conceit of the Atheiſt I take to be a convincing argument againſt him, <hi>Jamblicus</hi> a Heathen affirms, that Religion is implanted in the mind of Man, even before he has any uſe of reaſon, and we find by ſad experience, that Religion little prevails with the generality of Men to reſtrain them from Wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs, and that if the ſeverity of humane Laws did not ſcare them, there would ſcarce be any civility or Government in the World, there is no humane invention neceſſary for the life of Man, but a time may be aſſigned, either when it begun, or before it begun, but no time can be aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned, when Religion firſt began or before it began.</p>
            <p>The Atheiſt objects how we came to know of ſuch a general con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent; I anſwer, eaſily both from Geographers and Hiſtoriographers, both antient and modern, who give not only a deſcription of the known World, but Hiſtories of their manners, and have taken notice of ſome particular Atheiſts, but never branded any Nation or Country with it, not <hi>Herodotus,</hi> nor <hi>Strubonor, Ptolomy,</hi> nor <hi>Plinie, &amp;c.</hi> that have mark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:57480:8"/>with great curioſity the memorable things of every Country, nor of later time <hi>Munſter</hi> in his Coſmography, nor <hi>Ortelius</hi> in his <hi>Theatrum Mundi,</hi> ſo that if we cannot find by authority of Hiſtory, either anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent or modern, that Atheiſme overſpread any Nation, as other ſins re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markably have done, why ſhould we be ſo light as to believe there is any ſuch.</p>
            <p>But becauſe arguments from authority do not follow negatively, I ſhall prove it affirmatively, and then incite two excellent Hiſtorians of good Authority (1) <hi>Purchas</hi> his Pilgrimage, and <hi>Grimſtons</hi> Eſtates and Empires of the World, both moſt accurately deſcribing not only each Country, but the manners, Government, Riches, and Religions of each, ſo that the Atheiſt cannot name to us any Nation, but we can name a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain to him their Religion, and that they are not of his.</p>
            <p>All People inhabiting the whole Earth are either Chriſtians who wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip the Trinity, or <hi>Mahometans</hi> and <hi>Jews</hi> who worſhip the Creator, or pure <hi>Gentiles</hi> who worſhip the Stars and other Creatures, or Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters who worſhip Images, into theſe four Sects the World is Quarter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and all theſe to be found in every quarter of it, though Chriſtians do hold the predominancy in <hi>Europe, Mahometans</hi> in <hi>Aſia, Gentiles</hi> in <hi>Africa,</hi> and <hi>Idolaters</hi> in <hi>America,</hi> ſo that all of them be worſhippers, and all have their Gods.</p>
            <p>And that the forementioned Writers do neither abuſe us, or have been abuſed themſelves, we find all verified by Travellers, who have been Eye-witneſſes which is the beſt Authority, wherein we can have no better Teſtimony than thoſe of our own Nation, who have taken more pains in ſearching out the World, than any People of the World, as appears, by Mr. <hi>Hackluit</hi> in collecting our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Voyages, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt whom there are two <hi>Engliſh</hi> Gentlemen mentioned, who have compaſſed the whole Earth, the firſt Sir <hi>Francis Drake,</hi> who in his far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theſt Travels to the North-weſt, taking Land <hi>in nova Albion</hi> ſaw there the Savages buſied about a ſacrifice, who ſuppoſing our Men to be Gods, divers times offered to do their Sacrifices to them, which they never would have done, had they not been perſuaded that there is a God, and that offering ſacrifice is part of his Worſhip.</p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:57480:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>The other Captain <hi>Cavendiſh,</hi> who in his fartheſt Travels to the South-eaſt, Landing in the Iſle of <hi>Capal,</hi> obſerved the Inhabitants to be Worſhippers of the Devil, and the like may be obſerved in divers o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of their Voyages, who in the fartheſt and moſt remote parts could never find any Nation of Atheiſts, which juſtifies <hi>Plutarchs</hi> obſervation, that if a Man ſhould Travel through the whole Earth, he might hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pily meet with ſome People without Cloathes or Governours, but none without Gods, and ſome worſhip vile and baſe things, but rather them than no God, which proves the natural inſtinct of a deity implanted by God in all Men, we find the Heathens differing in the nature of the true God, but all agree there is a God, and 'tis <hi>Tully</hi>'s obſervation <hi>nulla gens tam fera quae Deum aliquem non agnoſcat,</hi> there is no Nation ſo ſavage, but they do acknowledge ſome God.</p>
            <p>But it may upon probable grounds be doubted, whither thoſe Men whom the Heathens have branded for Atheiſts, were pure Atheiſts ſuch as totally and conſtantly denyed any deity, for if he believe any one God, though he deny the reſt, or confeſs God in the end whom in the beginning he denyed, he cannot truly and properly be ſaid to be an Atheiſt, and firſt for <hi>Diagoras,</hi> who in their reckoning is the moſt noted Man of all of them, and the firſt ring-leader of their impious profeſſion, the reſt being counted but his followers, and yet the action which the <hi>Athenians</hi> ſo ſeverely commenced againſt him, and offering a great ſumm to any that would kill him, was no more but this that he did elimate, and divulge the Myſteries of the Gods, and by deri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding them avert and turn Men from them, ſo that <hi>Diagoras</hi> his crime was not that he denyed all Gods, but that he denyed the <hi>Athenians</hi> Gods, which he might do upon the filthineſs of their Ceremonies, and barbarouſneſs of their Sacrifices, and he might hereby diſcover the <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thenians</hi> Gods to be falſe, though perhaps he could not light upon or diſcover the true one, but that <hi>Diagoras</hi> was not a mere Atheiſt, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears, for that in the beginning of his Verſes as <hi>Morney</hi> áffirms he makes this profeſſion (which is the foundation of all Religion) that all things are ruled by one moſt high God.</p>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:57480:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Next conſider <hi>Protagoras</hi> whom the <hi>Athenians</hi> condemned for an Atheiſt, yet not for denying God but for ſeeming to doubt of him, becauſe in the beginning of his book he propounded this Probleme, <hi>de Diis Statuere nequeo,</hi> I cannot determine whether they be or not, for which the <hi>Athenians</hi> condemned him to Exile, and his Book to be burned, now doubting implies not <hi>Atheiſm,</hi> for dives of the Prophets doubted, and <hi>Job</hi> 24.1. doubts of Gods all-ſeeing Providence, this doubting may argue a weak faith in God for the preſent, but could not conclude their denying of God, and no more could it do in him.</p>
            <p>Next <hi>Eumerus</hi> was condemned for an Atheiſt, whoſe opinion <hi>Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doret</hi> affirms to have been <hi>profanam indeitatem</hi> a profane denying of the Gods, but yet it appears it was not a general denying of all Gods, but denying the Heathen Gods affirming them to be but Men, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it appears, that <hi>Eumerus</hi> his Atheiſme was not to divulge an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truth againſt the true God, but a truth againſt the falſe Gods, and the rather may this be believed to be true, becauſe <hi>Theophilus An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioche</hi> thus reports, that <hi>Eumerus</hi> did hold not only <hi>animae immortalita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem,</hi> but alſo <hi>Dei unitatem,</hi> not only the immortality of the Soul, but the unity of the Deity, which may probably be thought to be his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cantation, if ever before he had denyed there was a God.</p>
            <p>For <hi>Theodorus</hi> though it ſhould be granted, that he generally deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed there was a God, yet it cannot be affirmed that he conſtantly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyed it, for he fell in the end to that madneſs, as ridiculouſly to confeſs that himſelf was a God.</p>
            <p>As for <hi>Epicurus</hi> he denyed not Gods eſſence, but his Providence be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving there was a God, that did neither evil nor good, as <hi>Tully</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firms, and ſo for <hi>I hericides, Dioniſius,</hi> and the reſt <hi>Laertius</hi> gives a full account of them accordingly, but ſuppoſe all thoſe few that have been branded for Atheiſts were abſolute ones, wholly denying a God is it not a great madneſs for the Atheiſts of our times, to take up their im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piety that has been exploded, and hiſt off the Stage of the World in all Ages, by the judgment and conſent of the ableſt Philoſophers, and Learnedſt both of Heathens and Chriſtians, to whom they are infinitely ſhort in number, and as much in Learning.</p>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:57480:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>But as pride was the Father of Atheiſme amongſt the Philoſophers, who gloried in oppoſing one another, and being the Author of ſome new opinion, ſo 'tis to be feared too juſtly, in that the wickedneſs and debauchery of our later times, as the Apoſtle tells us, there ſhould come Mockers living after their own luſts, has been the occaſion of ſome Mens continuing, that horrid impiety being abhorred of God, and all good Men, having no other way to give a ſeeming counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance to their impiety, but to graft it upon the old dry ſtock of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theiſme, and ſo by their jollities and profaneneſs, make it their buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to ſtifle their Conſciences, and hating the light, leaſt their evil deeds ſhould be reproved.</p>
            <p>But herein the Atheiſt is much diſapointed of his great End, being not to ſerve and not to fear, as for ſerving ſurely there is not greater Slave in the World, than he that is a Slave to his Luſts, as every luxurious and debauched Perſon is, endeavouring to caſt off God, and ſet up his Luſts to rule over him, which he readily obeys, it being moſt true, which <hi>Cicero</hi> ſays, <hi>omnes improbi ſervi</hi> all wicked Men are Slaves, and therefore the Atheiſt is very far from that ſuppoſed liberty (in chooſing of his Atheiſme) he has promiſed to himſelf, being thereby made a Servant not only of many Maſters, but alſo of moſt baſe and unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy ones, whilſt virtue is wholly ſlighted by him, accounting it mean and baſe, whereas 'tis the greateſt honour to be vertuous, and that there is nothing ſo mean and baſe as vice, or ſo unworthy a Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man; for <hi>nobilitas ſola atque unica virtus,</hi> 'twas the reſolution of <hi>Seneca</hi> that was an Heathen, <hi>licet Deus neſciret, nec homo puniret peccatum non tamen peccarem ob peccati vilitatem,</hi> though God did not know nor Man would not puniſh Sin, yet I would not commit ſin for the baſeneſs of it, beſides 'tis far eaſier for Men to be virtuous than vitious.</p>
            <p>And as to the ſervile fear the Atheiſt would free himſelf from, he rather increaſes it, for there is no Man that is afraid of God, ſo much as they that would ſeem to fear him leaſt, none ſo baſely fears him.. as thoſe that ſeem moſt to contemn him, and this ſlaviſh fear and ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour oft falls upon them in their health and greateſt granduieur, <hi>Suetoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi> tells us that <hi>Caligula</hi> that deſpiſed all Gods, and would be a God
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:57480:10"/>himſelf and to that purpoſe, had a Temple, Altars and Prieſts, yet if there happened any great Thunder clap, would get under his Bed to ſave himſelf.</p>
            <p>But this fear terrifies the Atheiſt moſt when he comesto dye not ſo much the fear of Death, as what ſhall become of him after Death, <hi>Laertius</hi> gives us an inſtance of <hi>Bion</hi> of <hi>Boriſthenes</hi> one of the moſt obdurate A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theiſts, that when in his ſickneſs he perceived he muſt dye, that he would rather have endured any Torment than have dyed, fearing he ſhould be committed by God whom he had denyed; unto the Devil to be Torment<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and therefore put out his hand to him, hoping to Cajole him to be kind to him with this flattering Salutation <hi>Salve Pluto Salve,</hi> welcome Devil welcome, it ſeem's he did acknowledge there was a Devil, and then probably that there was a God, if not; then he made the Devil whom he was afraid of his God, and ſo dyed not an abſolute Atheiſt, And <hi>Cicero</hi> tells us of <hi>Epicurus,</hi> that though no Man ſeemed more to contemn God and Death, yet no Man more feared both the one; and the other, and we have a late inſtance of one of our own Nation, the Lord, <hi>R.</hi> a Man of a Luxuriant wit and bad life who prided himſelf in Atheiſm, and took a delight in propagating of it, who when he fell ſick of the diſeaſe where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of he dyed, how ſadly he bewailed his Impiety, ſeriouſly recanted it, and made proteſtation if God would ſpare his life, he would be as zealous in aſſerting the true God, as ever he had been in denying him, and would atteſt the reality of his Converſion by a pious Converſation.</p>
            <p>Now this inward fear which the Atheiſt has of God and outwardly bewrayes on ſeveral occaſions is no leſs an Argument, that he believes there is a God, then if he ſhould plainly confeſs it in word, and is indeed a far greater, for that this is real, and the other but verbal, and this is the reſult of Conſcience which God hath planted in every Man as his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puty to inform what is Good, and what is Evil.</p>
            <p>I queſtion whither there ever was or can be in the World an inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted, and internal denyal of the being of a God, or that Men (unleſs we can ſuppoſe Conſcience utterly dead) can arrive to ſuch a degree of Impiety for before they can ſtifle ſuch ſentiments in them (whatever they may Aſſert) they muſt be utter ſtrangers to the Common Conceptions of reaſon, and deſpoil themſelves of their own humanity, he that dares
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:57480:10"/>deny a God with his lips, ſets up ſome thing or other as a God in his heart, is it not Lamentable that this ſacred truth conſented to by all Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, which is the bond of civil ſocieties, and force of all order in the World, ſhould not only be denyed with a bare face, and diſputed againſt in Companies, and the Glory of a wiſe Creator aſcribed to an unintelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent nature or blind chance, are not ſuch worſe than the Heathens, they worſhiped many Gods, theſe none, they preſerved a Notion of God in the World, under a diſguiſe of <hi>Images,</hi> theſe would Baniſh him both from Earth and Heaven, and demoliſh the Statues of him in their own Conſciences, they degraded him, theſe would deſtroy him, they coupled Creatures with him, theſe would make him worſe than the Creature a meer nothing for that Earth is become hereby worſe than Hell, Hell that receives ſuch perſons in this point reformes them, the Devil that rejoyces at their wickedneſs, know's them to be in an error, for he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieves and Trembles, this muſt needs be a forerunner of ſore Judgment boldneſs in ſin, is a preſage of vengeance eſpecially when the honour of God is more Particularly concern'd therein it tends to the overturn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of humane ſocieties, and God appears not in ſuch viſible Judgments againſt ſin immediately committed againſt himſelf as in the caſe of thoſe ſins that are deſtructive to humane ſociety Atheiſme, is point blank againſt the glory of God in Creation and Redemption, and pronounces at one breath both the Creator and all the acts of Religion uſeleſs and in ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficant.</p>
            <p>And yet 'tis impoſſible for the Atheiſt to demonſtrate there is no God, he cannot uſe any <hi>Medium</hi> but will fall in as a proof for his exiſtence rather than againſt it, the pretences of the Atheiſt are ſo Ridiculous, that they are not worth mentioning, as that he never ſaw God, and therefore knows not how to believe ſuch a being, and that he cannot Comprehend him, he would not be infinite if he were Comprehenſible, or to be determined by our ſight, the Atheiſt cannot ſee his own Life, and yet he believes he lives, he cannot ſee his own Soul, yet he knows he has one by his thinking power, none ſees the air he lives and breaths in, but the Atheiſt, and all Men know there is air as well as Earth, and Water which they continually ſee, though they ſee not the other.</p>
            <p>'Tis a cogent argument, that there is a God by the fear and dread of Man upon the Beaſts, as <hi>Lions, Tygers, Bares,</hi> &amp;c. Which would ſoon de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:57480:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>Man, were it not for that reſtraint, is put upon their Nature, which can be from none but God, as he promiſed in his word, for if Man made himſelf he could not have reſtrained the Nature of the Beaſts, if Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture had made him, it had been a Contradiction in her to change their Nature, therefore it muſt be God only.</p>
            <p>And if there be not a God, how comes it to paſs, that the Sea which is agreed to be bigger and higher than the Land, ſhould contrary to the Nature of Water (which is to diffuſe it ſelf) be reſtrained by a low ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy ſhore, from overflowing the Earth, which cannot be but by that God that has ſet it, its bounds, and ſays hitherto, ſhall you come, and no fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and that the Sea is higher then the Land, is demonſtrable by the Springs which under <hi>Ariſtotles</hi> favour, have another cauſe then what he aſſerts. The true cauſe of the Springs being the Waters of the Sea which paſſes through the ſmall Crannies, and mealus of the Earth, which ſweetens it by its paſſage, and breaks out into Springs, which we ſee many times riſe in High Hills, the reaſon of which is, that the Sea being as high, or higher then thoſe Hills, the Water is forced to riſe ſo high, for it would elſe be contrary to the Nature of Water to aſcend to thoſe Hills, we ſee it manifeſt by leading Water from a Spring-head by Pipes or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe, that as high as the Spring-head is ſo high it will force the Water to riſe whither it is carryed.</p>
            <p>I would aske the Atheiſt how he came into the World, whither at the beginning of the World, for the World had a beginning, for the matter of the World cannot be Eternal, matter cannot ſubſiſt without form, nor put on any form without the action of ſome cauſe, this cauſe muſt be in being before it acted, that which is not cannot act, the cauſe of the World muſt neceſſarily exiſt before any matter was endued with any form mer, that therefore cannot be Eternal before which another did ſubſiſt, if it were from Eternity, it would not be ſubject to mutation, if the whole was from Eternity, why not alſo the parts, what makes the changes ſo viſible then, Eternity would exempt it from mutability, if the World were Eternal, it muſt have been in the ſame poſture it is now, in a ſtate of Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration and Corruption, and ſo Corruption muſt have been as Eternal as Generation, and then things that doe generate, and Corruption muſt have Eternally been, and Eternally not have been, there muſt be ſome firſt way to ſet Generation on foot, and reaſon is quite bewitched, and cannot
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:57480:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>return into a right way of Conception till it conceive one firſt of every kind, one firſt Man, one firſt Animal one firſt Plant whence others do proceed, the Argument is unanſwerable, and the wiſeſt Atheiſt (if any Atheiſt can be called wiſe) cannot unlooſe the knot.</p>
            <p>The World could not be made by an aſſembly of attomes, as ſome fooliſhly fancy for there muſt be ſome infinite intelligent cauſe that made them, ſome cauſe that ſeparated them, ſome cauſe that mingled them together For piling up ſo comly a Structure as the Word, 'tis moſt abſurd to think they ſhould meet together by hazard, and Rank them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in that order we ſee without a higher and wiſe agent.</p>
            <p>Nor could Nature make the World, for before the World was made, there was nothing for Nature to exerciſe it ſelfe, for Nature is but <hi>vis &amp; Petentia</hi> a force and power which is Implanted in every ſpecies from the Creation, and <hi>Extra Subjectum natura nunquam ſubſiſtit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>'Tis the general conſent both of Chriſtians and Heathens, 1. That there is nothing in Nature, but it has its cauſe 2. That nothing in Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture is the cauſe of it ſelf 3. That amongſt all the cauſes, there is one ſupream firſt cauſe, which is the true cauſe of all the reſt, 4. That the firſt cauſe of all things is nothing elſe but God, then God muſt be the Creator of the World, and all things in it, and then of Man alſo.</p>
            <p>For Man had a Beginning, there's no Man in the World but was ſome Years ago no Man, if every Man we ſee, had a Beginning, then the firſt Man alſo had a Beginning, if we pitch on ſome Man that was un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>born, that firſt Men muſt either be Eternal, that cannot be, for he that has no beginning and has no end, or he muſt ſpring out of the Earth as Plants and Trees do, that cannot be, why ſhould not the Earth produce Men to this day, as it does Plants and Trees, nor came Man into the World by chance, why has not chance produced the like in the long time the World has ſtood, he was therefore made and muſt have ſome cauſe that made him, which can be no other than God, who made him after his own image and indued him with an Immortal Soul.</p>
            <p>And as God made the World and all things in it by his Power, ſo by his Providence does he rule and governs it, 'twas a brutiſh opinion of <hi>Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curus,</hi> who acknowledged there was a God, yet denyed his Providence,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:57480:12"/>as if he had made the World only to look upon and not govern and take care of it, who is it that bridles the unruly paſſions of Men, that elſe would deſtroy one another, who tempers the contrary nature of the Elements, that elſe would ruine the World and bring it to a <hi>Chaos,</hi> ſo that they are brought into ſuch a harmony as conduces to the Preſervation of it, whence came thoſe miracles which are againſt the order of nature mentioned in the Scripture to be done by Chriſt, acknowledged to be done by him, both by <hi>Heathens</hi> and the <hi>Jews</hi> his Enemies, and that miraculous Ecclipſe of the Sun, at his paſſion quite againſt the rule of nature, the Moon being then in oppoſition to the Sun, which the <hi>Heathens</hi> took ſo much notice of and wondred at, why the Sun that heats the World being ſo vaſt a Body com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pured to be 166 times bigger than the Earth, and to move a Million of Miles every hour, ſhould not by its ſo ſwift and rapid motion, ſet the World on Fire, if God did not govern the World, Creation implies Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, and if God did not govern the World, all his attributes would be uſeleſs, for to what purpoſe ſhould he be Omniſcient, Omnipotent, Om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nipreſent, Wiſe, Juſt and Good, if he did not exerciſe them in governing the World, ſo that to deny Gods Providence is all one, as to deny there is a God.</p>
            <p>But the Atheiſt will not believe he has an Immortal Soul, for as he lives like the Beaſts that periſh, ſo he hopes he ſhall dye, but he'l find himſelf deceived in his later end, his reaſon againſt the Immortality of the Soul is becauſe 'tis ſays he, an impoſſible thing for a Mortal Man to beget an Immortal Soul, but upon a ſerious conſideration it will appear, there is neither impoſſibility or irrationality in it, for with God all things are poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, beſides 'tis not unreaſonable to think, that God that made Man af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter his own Image, and the chiefeſt of the Creatures here below, for whoſe uſe they were all made, ſhould endue him with a faculty to beget a Man like himſelf, and not leave him in a worſe condition than the meaneſt of the Beaſts, we read <hi>Gen.</hi> 5. <hi>Adam</hi> begat a Son in his own likeneſs, which could not be if the Soul as well as the Body came not from him, <hi>Generatio eſt totius compoſiti, &amp; naturaliſſimum eſt ut quodlibet vivens ex ſe ſimilem ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciem procreet,</hi> Generation is of the whole, and 'tis moſt natural that every living thing ſhould procreate the like ſpecies.</p>
            <p>But ſome to avoid the ſeeming impoſſibility of a Mortal Mans begetting an Immortal Soul, have and do hold that God Creates the Souls of all Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple that are Born, but this ſeems repugnant to his ſeventh days reſt from his work of Creation, and beſides ſhould we put God to the Creating ſo
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:57480:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>many Thouſand Souls, that are every day Born in the World, we ſhould put him to a greater work every day, than the whole Creation of the World was in Six days, and beſides it would be unaccountable, that if God Create the Soul, which muſt come pure from him, how that Soul ſhould be infected with <hi>Adams</hi> ſin, and when 'tis asked when that Soul is Created and put into Man, the anſwer is <hi>Creando infunditur infundendo cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atur,</hi> an intelligible Riddle, the 12 <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> I take to be no <hi>cogent objection</hi> againſt it, which ſays duſt returns to the Earth as it was, and the Spirit to God that gave it (1) to <hi>Adam,</hi> and ſo derived from him to all his Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterity, and therefore I ſee nothing repugnant, either to the word of God or reaſon in holding the Soul to be extradate by Generation.</p>
            <p>I thought to have ſaid a word or two to the practical Atheiſt, who I take to be as bad as the other, who though he confeſs God with his Mouth, yet in his Works denies him, whoſe ſin againſt Chriſt is worſe than the <hi>Jews</hi> in Crucifying him, for they knew not what they did, therefore he prays they may be forgiven, but theſe by their bold and preſumptuous ſins Crucifie him dayly, and put him to an open ſhame, but reſolving to keep to my intended brevity, I leave both to the farther conſideration of thoſe that have the conduct of Souls, to whom it does more properly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long, wiſhing that they not only from the Preſs, but oftener from the Pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pit, would make it their buſineſs to convince the People, that there is a God, and that the People would follow the Apoſtles advice, obey them that have the overſight of you, and ſubmit your ſelves for they watch for your Souls, as they that muſt give account, and then the People being perſwaded that there is a God, and that God Eternal, Omnipotent, Om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nipreſent, Omniſcient, Holy and Juſt, and that there is a day of Judgment a Hell to puniſh Eternally all wicked and obſtinate Sinners, and a Heaven to reward with Eternal Happineſs, thoſe that live ſoberly and piouſly in the fear of God, it is to be hoped the wicked World would prove better, and Virtue and Piety become as much invogue, as Atheiſme and profane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs is now.</p>
            <byline>By a lover of God and the Truth.</byline>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
